this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host johannesproni and today
we'll be discussing the trade-offs
between code quality and performance
with casimiratori because it's the host
of handmade hero and educational
programming cities and the lead
programmer at Molly rocket on 1935 which
is an upcoming interactive narrative
game about organized crime in the 1930s
New York his past projects include the
granny animations SDK blink 2 and the
witness because his past results
contribution include the NY linear
quaternion blend the immediate mode
graphical user interface and the first
geometric optimization for the Gilbert
Johnson 30 algorithm his current
research interests include interactive
fiction concurrent Computing and
operating system architecture Casey
welcome to software engineered radio
thanks so much for having me on your
program well thank you for coming let's
start now this interview is actually
been prompted by your blog entry with a
video entitled clean called horrible
performance published at the end of
February this year which costs let's say
some strong reactions yeah yes
certainly we did with many agreeing with
your points and many other disagreeing
very strongly as well so you polarize
the audience a bit from what I could
tell in in many ways I seem to have
given the audience an excuse to argue
amongst themselves more than anything
there were so many arguments between
people that did not involve me that came
out of this video that that seemed to be
the biggest actual result or the thing
that it caused the most was other
arguments that I was not even aware of
okay so can you actually give us a very
brief summary of the main points of the
video for the listeners that maybe
haven't seen the video yet I can also
perhaps give a little bit more context
to the video because one of the things
that is interesting about the video is
it comes from a course that I made and
nobody really knows the context of it if
they haven't looked at that course for
example they're just seeing like this
little slice right so I have a sub stack
it's at computer enhanced.com and on
there there's like a table of contents
that has the listing of what is in this
course and the first thing that it has
in this course is a prologue and the
prologue is not designed to teach anyone
any of the concepts yet it's just
designed to teach people I should say
that the course is about understanding
performance or being aware of
performance it's designed to teach
people effectively like what are the
things that can affect performance and
I've got a thing in there about IPC
about multi-threading about cash you
know that sort of stuff and this
material for the clean code horrible
performance was something that I
basically included as a bonus video that
didn't quite make the cut for the
prologue because I was like yeah you
know virtual functions are kind of this
subset of a different thing we talked
about which was this sort of idea of
waste which is making the CPU do things
that you really didn't need it to do and
so this is just like a little tiny
snippet from this larger context and of
course it's the only thing that anyone
has really seen outside of the people
taking the course which it's a paid
course so I don't blame people like they
don't want to go take the course totally
fine by me but this video has to be
understood as something that is part of
the larger context of things you need to
be aware of when you're thinking about
performance so in this particular video
what I talk about is the fact that in a
lot of the sort of traditional textbooks
that people cite when they talk about
clean code including I don't say this
overtly in the video but including the
book that is literally called clean code
and is the first hit on Google if you
search for the word clean code so it is
if a novice who does not have their own
idea about what clean code is was to
type clean code into Google and hit
return they will find like that book
they will also find right on that front
page like summaries of the rules from
that book which include the rules I use
in the video and so on so in this video
I go over what some of those rules are
and specifically what some of the rules
are that actually are directly related
to code architecture because some of the
rules when people talk about clean code
have nothing to do with code
architecture they're things like what do
we name variable names well that's about
readability to the programmer but it
will not affect the program at all so we
the code architecture mean things that
actually influence the runtime behavior
of the program somehow after compilation
maybe or the influence literally what
the structure of the program is in any
analysis even separate from the compiler
because you are making choices about
what code can and cannot go together to
give a simple example there's a book on
refactoring by Martin Fowler there will
be literally parts that say oh we were
doing these two things inside one Loop
and instead I'm going to break it into
two loops and do one thing in each Loop
that is a transformation of the code
that assuming those two Loops are not
analyzable and fusible by the compiler
anymore because you've moved them then
that is literally just a different
program the compiler can never generate
the same program from that thing that
you've done right so when I say that
they affect the architecture of the
program what I mean is the two source
code sets can no longer generate the
same program by any compiler that we
currently have like maybe some future
compiler could undo that change because
it's way smarter you know I mean the the
new AI is descend and they can analyze
what you've done and say oh this person
broke those two Loops apart I'm going to
use them together right but currently
the technology we have doesn't do these
Transformations so I took the rules I
could find in there that were specific
they were ones that were like you should
do these Transformations like prefer
this to that that had to do with
architecture and I was just looking at
them and going like you know these are
basically just really bad for
performance in most languages if you
apply these rules they're telling you to
do things like using inheritance
hierarchies and using like Dynamic
dispatch a lot of times and when you
actually look at what those transforms
do to code it all just slows it down it
never speeds it up it can only slow it
down and it slows it down in ways that
that most people don't even appreciate
and again this is stuff we cover later
in the course this video isn't meant to
give you a full understanding of why but
most people look at that video and
because I guess I don't know this is
just what they think in their head is
happening or something they think that
I'm only talking about the cost of
calling through a v table but that's not
the only cost there are also a lot of
optimization costs you pay because when
you call through a virtual function in
languages like C plus if the compiler
doesn't directly know exactly what type
it's dealing with it cannot optimize
through that virtual function call and
that is by far the biggest cost not the
dispatch the dispatch can be bad as well
but it's the optimization cost so I was
trying to just show like I showed with
the other things in the prologue of this
course hey these are all real things
like when I'm talking about this I'm not
talking about abstract things like when
I said some of the things in there were
like multi-threading or IPC I didn't
want to just throw out the terms I want
to show you little easy to understand
Snippets of code where all I have to do
is one little tiny change and oh it gets
a lot slower right and I did that for
everything I did that for IPC I did that
for multi-threaded I did that for
caching and this was just one that I did
for like hey virtual functions really
bad right so I can understand why people
when that's all they've seen they think
maybe that I'm saying that like oh
virtual functions are like the only
thing that's wrong with like for cobras
like no it's just one of many things
that are bad techniques and so that's
you know kind of I think what incited
the sort of large amounts of reactions
to it okay a few questions about some of
the aspects okay so I don't really want
to focus on the video per se I want to
focus here on the trade-offs if you like
so we'll talk about now a performance
then later maybe a bit about what let's
call it good code looks like because
clean code seems to be a trademark you
know they're talking about think of the
fight that is there seems to be has some
kind of specific meaning nowadays so
let's say good code yeah the first
question I had is that I noticed that in
in the video You focus a lot on CPU
Cycles optimizing for CPU Cycles now in
many modern applications actually have a
network or IO bound so in this context
what is your view about applying clean
code principles so let me give you an
example who said how virtual functions
can be very expensive but when you are
IO bound the network bound probably the
cost is not that much in the grand
scheme of things so I'd like to
understand your position of the clinical
principles if they are still good bad I
don't know even in context you have the
performances are actually influenced by
other aspects totally understand the
question and I think for me I I always
have sort of a difficult time with the
specifics of that particular analysis so
personally
I've never seen a program that has those
characteristics meaning I've never
actually seen a program that is actually
I O bound I have seen programs that were
written in such a way that they become i
o bound but the actual nature of the
thing the program is doing is almost
never i o bound and the reason I say
that is because when I say never I mean
in a current context obviously if we
rewind the tape to 1970 it's pretty easy
to find something that might be bound by
a spinning tape drive or something like
this but modern i o subsystems deliver
massive throughput modern Network
architectures deliver massive throughput
with extremely low latency I mean my
ping times from my home in rural
Washington are sub 10 millisecond ping
times to Major servers so when people
say that they're i o bound usually when
they say that it's because the way they
structured their program artificially
made it I O bound and there's a lot of
ways that this happens so for example if
you structure your communication with a
server so that you've basically just not
really thought about how you're going to
request things and you haven't really
thought about which side is going to do
which computations and things like that
you will often see network-based
programs for example doing linear sets
of dependent i o operations they'll send
one small thing over to the server and
the server will send some small thing
back the client will do a little bit of
work and then send another thing over
wait for the response and so on right
you can actually see this if you open up
a lot of web pages that load slowly you
mean it basically applications that are
very chatty in a way so lots of small
requests back and forth their serial
dependency chains right they're a Serial
chain of things that it has to wait on
the io4 and if you look at a lot of web
pages you'll see this is why they're
slow they'll be these long diagonal
lines of basically like Network weights
right
now if you actually go to look at what
it's doing
there's usually no actual reason that
the programmer had to have structured it
they were in control of both sides and
they merely chose to do it this way so
then they say well it doesn't matter how
slow my JavaScript stuff is here because
most of my time is waiting on the search
like well no that's not actually true
that's just because you also didn't fix
the way you were doing Uriah right does
that make sense I understand your point
but what I'm thinking is also so for
example I've experienced mostly with
Enterprise systems if you want to call
this big
is running behind for some big Banks or
big companies that are used by lots of
people and usually have to do to deal
with the quite big databases so in those
situations sometimes queries are not as
fast as you would wish them to be even
if you optimize as much as you can the
database for because there is simply a
lot of data yeah
so in those situations you really become
IO bound of course sometimes things are
not done properly as it is the case but
even when they are done properly the
difference between the CPU performance
and the performance of the i o can be
really dramatic there so these are the
kind of systems I'm thinking of but I
guess I don't know why a database system
would be i o Bound in that sense right
like I mean are you talking about the
database does not have the ability to be
distributed or do memory caching I'm
talking from the interaction with the
database from the point of view of the
service running you know running the
query so my service needs to read
something from the database runs a query
receives the data back
this operation is actually very often
time consuming depending on the amount
of data you have of course also the
setup matters there are lots of things
but in general
the performance of these operations is
much much slower than what you have at
the CPU lever yeah well so I obviously
don't disagree with the fact that if you
have two things that need to communicate
and one of them is performing slowly
that the other one then has the ability
to perform more slowly if you like
without actually affecting the runtime
of the program however
what you have done if that's the design
philosophy in other words if your
philosophy is well we'll take whatever
the slowest piece of our system is and
just design everything else to be as
slow as that thing is now you've
basically guaranteed that you can't
really optimize your database because if
you now decide well you know what we
want to speed up this system so we go
and we optimize the database and then
for some reason nothing gets faster Why
didn't it get faster well because all of
our other things were taking advantage
of the fact that that piece was slow so
we've basically just we've what we've
done there is we've solidified low
performance into our architecture which
I again wouldn't approve of let's see if
I'm understanding what they're saying
basically are saying
if you say that the database is the is
the bottleneck yeah and so because of
that you take less care of the code of
your service
it's like well
then if you try to improve things on the
database they won't give you an
advantage because anyway your service is
sluggish so you're saying in other terms
that's no excuse to actually write code
that is low on your service to start it
yes and I will go you one better and say
we have examples of this in the wild so
this isn't hypothetical a recent video I
did is called performance excuses
debunked I think and what I do in that
video is I just go through all of the
performance announcements that have been
made at like Facebook Uber Twitter where
they announce hey we improved
performance by this much and here's what
we did if you go look for example at
Facebook's performance announcements you
will actually see announcements where
they're like we tried to speed up the
server but we quickly hit a limit to how
much we could speed up the server
because our web front ends were so slow
that it didn't matter how fast we turned
around the responses right so the case
you're talking about it literally
happened and we have like documented
proof of it happening and then they just
all you end up doing is then you have to
flip around and go all right now we got
to rewrite our front ends because they
were all written to be slow and so when
we sped up our back end nothing happened
right so the way I look at it is when
people make the claim that they are i o
bound or that they are bound by
something where it doesn't matter how
they architected their software
even if they're right which oftentimes I
think they say that and it's not really
true like they haven't actually analyzed
that program to prove that that's true
but let's say some people have and
they're right I still think it's a poor
choice because all you're really doing
is then making it harder for the future
team that's going to have to improve
this system to actually make those
improvements you're going to upgrade
your hardware and on your server and
you're not going to get any faster and
the reason is because you had all these
slow front ends that were wasting a
bunch of time right okay
let's move on now one of the rules you
break in the video is called that code
should not know about the internals of
objects it's working with which is
basically the modularization mechanism
devised by David parnas in 1972 yeah
which nowadays is a kind of staple of
good system design for many reasons you
know flexibility comprehensibility
shortening of development and time if
the if you have different teams work in
different modules stuff like this
in the video by doing that you get a big
Improvement in performance at some point
so I have a couple of questions related
to this
the first one is what do you do in case
these objects you depend upon are
actually external libraries or
Frameworks you depend upon I mean do you
go there and check and try to depend on
implementation details that can give you
an advantage or your kind of live with
it and just use the public API even if
you go a bit slower what is your
approach with that
well I mean I don't know that I would
say that I have a particular approach
one way or the other but what I would
say is people do both of those things so
sometimes if you can live with whatever
the performances that you have then
you're like well I'm not going to touch
this particular libraries thing because
they're going to change it or they're
going to update it and I don't want to
have to create work for myself every
time they do and that's a trade-off you
can totally make other times when
performance is important people
literally do exactly what you said in
fact people have done exactly what you
said with libraries I've written because
there were we can go into this if at
some point if you want to but obviously
I used to ship literally commercial
libraries that's what my job was at rad
game tools to hundreds of game
developers had to use these libraries
and so on and in general what I try to
do is make actual contracts for data
types so I would try to basically say to
people okay anytime we have a data type
that we're very confident we don't need
to change we will expose it to you and
the reason What specifically that that
it makes it much easier for developers
to work with those data types because
now they can have their compiler see
them and even they don't necessarily
have to touch them but the fact that
they're exposed mean that the code gets
faster when they compile because their
code doesn't have to call Access or
functions that they can't see it can
just do those accesses in line and it
gets much faster but occasionally we
would have somewhere like these are
probably going to change and we would
keep those internal we wouldn't expose
the definition of those and sometimes
because I mean in games obviously
there's tight performance budgets
especially back in those days maybe not
So Much Anymore you would have people
who would even go and they would take
out the internal definition sometimes
use them and we're just like that's fine
as long as you know that we might change
these in the future so you're going to
have a little more work to do if you
want to roll that forward but in general
I would say the more important point in
that overall is that I think the idea
that you're supposed to hide as much as
possible from the people using your code
is actually not a very good idea and
it's not a very good idea for three
reasons really I would say say not you
know performance is only kind of one of
them the first reason is because if you
can solidify on a type and say this is
actually what it's really going to be
then you can expose that type and get
good performance benefits for people it
allows the compiler to do a lot of
things that it couldn't have done if it
was hidden so that's just a kind of a
good thing but number two is it also
AIDS in people's understanding of what
the code is actually doing and how so
the reason that I bring this up is
because a lot of times people who
advocate for clean code they say
something that I don't think is actually
true in practice which is that hiding
implementation details from people makes
it easier to understand what the code is
doing I don't actually think that's true
because most of the time when I need to
actually read people's code it's because
it is not doing something that I thought
it should be doing meaning if I'm ever
to go looking at what a library is doing
in the first place then that means it
didn't just do what I expected because
if it just did what I expected then I
just call the API and I never really
need to look at the code or understand
what it's doing right wouldn't that be
either a bug on the library or just
wrong expectation on your side both it
could be either right that is usually
when I'm reading the code I'm usually
reading the code either because there's
a bug in the library or because I
thought it was doing something that it
wasn't doing and the documentation maybe
doesn't say or whatever when I go to
read it the more layers of abstraction
and the more layers of encapsulation
that that library has put between me and
what's going on actually make it take
longer for me to find the problem and
this is why I feel that the claim that
it improves readability I wouldn't claim
it to be false but I would say that it's
dramatically overstated because a lot of
times I find it actually makes it harder
for me to do the work I need to do isn't
it actually two different definitions of
what readability means or
understandability means because my
understanding of information hiding is
that I expose what should matter to you
yeah this is what you know this is the
contract this is how the module works
and so you basically say okay you do
what I need fine you don't do what I
need I may look for something else what
you are saying is instead well if it
doesn't do what I expect I'm curious to
see what he's actually doing because I
may have a better understanding and
maybe get it to do what I want but it
seems to be a different a different
approach I don't know well you don't
really have the luxury of not using it
right I mean that's only at the very
start of a project if you're two years
into something and you use this database
or this module or whatever and your
whole program is built around that
module and you're shipping it in
production if you call some function and
it's not working or the latest update it
doesn't work or whatever you don't have
the luxury well we'll just do something
else that's not real programming right
that is not the reality of our lives our
lives are oh crap this thing is broken
somebody needs to go figure out why is
it something we're doing did we change
something in our code that maybe broke
what the library thought was is
happening or maybe the performance is
now a problem for some reason you know
that sort of thing okay let's move on
now I have the second question I said
before about this information hiding so
in a video when you say that you broke
the information hiding principle
basically to gain a performance
Advantage looking at the video from my
point of view you actually cheated
because you didn't really break anything
you look at that problem from a
different angle from what I can see so
from my point of view when I was seeing
the Cody wrote and stuff was just
modeling the problem in a different way
to satisfy different criteria in this
case higher performance yeah so can you
comment on that so I I guess I would say
I don't know that I have any particular
comment on it I could talk about I guess
why I don't see it that way but I don't
have a problem with someone who wants to
think about it that way so I wouldn't
necessarily disagree with that opinion
if you think about things in terms of
like there are certain ways of looking
at a problem and you thought it was a
different way of looking at it that's
fine with me but I can elaborate it more
if you'd like okay no that's fine
because it's simply the way the way I
saw that well I invite of course the
listeners to to look at your video the
link will be on the link section of the
the podcast here's the comment I guess I
could make on that so if you look at
what happens in typical code bases that
follow the polymorphism like don't use
ifs don't use switches use class
hierarchies sort of design pattern which
is actually quite common in the wild one
of the things that I didn't think was a
very accurate comment that people have
made about this video is that somehow
people don't do that lots of people do
that I assure you we can I can give you
tons of examples of people doing it but
it's a very common thing I agree that
some regions of the programming sphere
don't do it but it's not like nobody
does that anymore it's very common still
but anyway when you are presented with a
design like that and I think I said this
in the video when someone goes and needs
to optimize this code because they're
like this is running too slowly and we
want to speed it up if what they see is
a switch statement it's very easy for
you to basically turn a switch statement
into what I would call either a vector
complete or a merged case meaning
something that just does one computation
that does all the computations at once
and this is a very common technique in
Vector complete programming we do it all
the time when people aren't used to
programming Vector complete this is a
very foreign thing so I can understand
why it's like something that people
would be like I have no idea what this
is it's very weird but it's very
standard it's just standard Vector
complete stuff if you've ever done GPU
programming it's just a normal thing
that you do switch statements make it
very easy to see you're like oh okay
these people need to do these kind of
multipliers these people need to do
these kind of lookups and we just this
is the most straightforward merge I can
do and this will compute all of these
different quote unquote object types in
one block of code that doesn't have any
branches in it which again is crucial
for Vector completeness so it's a
standard thing that you would do if
instead said what you are presented with
as an Optimizer is a class hierarchy
this analysis takes way longer you have
to go through and untangle this class
hierarchy figure out what all the
different possible Leaf functions are
you don't even know what files those
might be and you probably have to use a
tool etc etc and so what I was trying to
show in the video was if someone now
needs to improve the performance of this
thing because again this is a course on
performance aware programming that this
comes from it is very simple to improve
the performance of a switch statement it
is much more time consuming to do the
same transform on a class hierarchy okay
I've got another question here instead
this is not related to this particular
aspect of code but is related to some of
the principles you touch than some of
the others you didn't really touch upon
in your video so there is some evidence
that this clean code principle at least
quite a few of them have some positive
effect on developers cognition that
means when you read code or write code
somehow is easier to understand or
easier to do stuff with the code you
know change it extend that is I put in
the links book that is called the
programmer's brain by feline hermans now
what is your opinion about those
principles looking at them just from
that perspective of actually
understandability extensibility so let's
say if performance was a known issue
which is obviously an abstract thing at
the moment but if it wasn't any issue
with those principles is there anything
that you still don't quite like or they
would be okay fine is a matter of
trade-offs I won't understand your
perspective on that I I would say that
it really depends on what the comparison
is or what the Baseline is I guess is
what I would say so when I have looked
at things like examples that people who
Advocate these particular clean code
principles when they do a comparison and
they're like okay this is more readable
when I've pulled it out into this class
Parky or something like that usually
when I see those my first thought is you
did not actually try to make the highly
readable and still quite performant
procedural version that doesn't actually
use the class hierarchy so I would say I
have two different opinions about this
particular thing if you are comparing
the virtual function class hierarchy
version to the messiest possible sort of
like old school tons of duplicated code
lots of pound ifs you know that sort of
thing version sorry to I probably
shouldn't say this but let's just say a
the gnu make code base as an example
right which is really hard to read
through and it's just got so much stuff
through and through it I agree I agree
that the class Harkey version looks
better on the other hand there are easy
ways in my opinion to make procedural
code very readable you pull out code
that's used multiple times into
functions that do what they need to do
you name those functions sensibly the
code is very readable at the end of that
process and in my opinion it's no
different in terms of cognition from the
class hierarchy version but it also
performs much faster so to me it's like
yeah I agree that there are code bases
who you could take and say hey the class
version is much more readable but I also
would have said well there's a better
way to have written that anyway that has
nothing to do with classes so why are we
claiming the advantage comes from the
classes as opposed to just not doing all
of these kind of other bad things you
know that were present another question
related to this so you seem to take
issue especially with a class hierarchy
small than anything else absolutely am I
correct yeah because that's what the
video is about right okay now what these
in your view actually good code you know
so clean code is one view as we said
before maybe clinkode at the moment has
a kind of specific meaning nowadays so
let's assume it's the meaning that you
find it a clean code book so let's
change time yeah so it's clean code is a
one view of what constitutes Google code
what is good code for you in your
specific opinion if I had to say the
general general principles that I look
for I would say number one is that the
code in general reads roughly like what
the program actually does so I tend to
think that good code reads like its
series of operations it's also one of
the reasons I don't super like class
hierarchies is because they tend to hide
a lot of what's actually going on in the
program and I don't tend to like that
right I tend to like code that reads
like what it does because to me that's
the most what I think about code
readability I don't think about just I
think I know what the code does I want
to actually know what the code does so I
like code that if I read it I am not
surprised by what I then find out the
code was really doing behind my back
right so I'd say that's thing number one
thing number two is that the code
minimizes the degree to which things I
might change in how the code operates
will not have to require equivalent
changes somewhere else that I don't know
about so for example if I have a piece
of code code and it's got this is a very
simple example but hopefully people
could extrapolate to more complex ones
and it's got a constant in it that's
like this is the radius of the Earth or
whatever if I want to change what I'm
considering the radius of the Earth I
don't want to find out later that
there's somewhere else in the code that
has to agree with this part of the code
that also has the earth radius encoded
somewhere else and you can imagine lots
of different versions of this that are
more complicated that aren't just a
constant they're some function that's
get called something about how a
database is locked that has to be
maintained I don't want there to be
times when I think I'm changing the only
piece of code that does something and
find out later there are these other
things that the programmer secretly had
agree that I had no way of knowing
number three would be that the code in
general is not doing anything that
precludes me from making sensible
optimizations to it later meaning it has
not been I guess the word factored is
probably what most people would use it
has not been factored in such a way that
precludes the possibility of future
optimization without a rewrite and I
know that's a very hard one that's
that's really that one is almost what my
course is about it's about how to write
code that doesn't prevent a future
Optimizer from actually making the code
run quickly and so that one would
probably be my third one because that I
think is probably the most difficult
thing of all to know how to do because
it requires you to understand what
people might need to do to optimize them
in the future but that to me is another
component of good code because otherwise
you get in these cycles and I documented
this in my performance excuses debunked
video you get in these bad cycles of
people having to constantly throw away
entire systems and rewrite them because
they were written in such a way that
precludes optimization so I think those
would probably be my three roughly if I
had to say okay follow up on this one so
looking at your videos you are keen on
objectively measurable criteria yes what
objective criteria can you apply to
assess the code goodness according into
your preferences so one that I'm sure
will be again since my other video was
already very controversial I don't mind
saying another thing which is
controversial which is that something
that I actually use actively all the
time when I am actually programming is I
check my lines of code and I don't do
this because I'm trying to optimize my
lines of code down to the smallest
actual number because that actually
isn't very useful I don't want to be
like doing weird tricks right and I use
lines of code only because I don't have
a convenient tool that measures
something better like number of
operations or those sorts of things but
I check my lines of code fairly
religiously and the reason for that is
because it's the best objective measure
that I've found for that first point
that I said which is that the code reads
like what it does because I find that a
lot of times if you start adding lots of
sort of like code that doesn't really do
anything like infrastructure like oh I'm
gonna create these class hierarchies or
I'm going to create these sort of
extraneous things that I'm use using to
sort of abstract the code or do things
like that I find that they tend to
balloon the lock count of things a good
example this would be like the llvm code
base or something where it takes 10 000
lines of code to do four lines of codes
worth of work or something right and I
try to keep that as close and to learn
sort of the correspondence if you will
of roughly how much lock in a particular
language I think corresponds to General
features to keep myself from going down
paths where it's like wait a minute am I
just massively over complicating what
this thing actually has to do so I feel
like that's a good objective metric we
should kind of like features per line of
code is something I kind of actually
want to keep a good handle on and
there's two reasons for this one is
because I find that it's easier to read
the code meaning it's easier if there's
less code I can read it I can understand
it I can keep it in my head the second
one is because it's easier to modify and
optimize the code oftentimes if there's
just not that much of it the more code I
have the harder my job is if I have to
go change something because oh my God
there's so much of it obviously that
means that if I want to change this
feature I'm going to be touching 10 000
lines of code instead of 100 lines of
code so I try to keep an eye on that and
then for the optimization one in general
I'm always measuring the performance of
the code I just keep that as a constant
thing so whenever I'm running a program
my programs always have performance
metrics on the side just by default and
I always watch those performance metrics
because I always want to make sure they
are reasonable if your current
performance metrics are pretty
reasonable then you're usually in good
shape for eventually someone optimizing
something whereas if your current
performance metrics are awful it's
probably a sign that you're doing some
things like those big long serial
dependency chains you've you've added
like this really inefficient way of
doing something that's going to be very
hard for someone to optimize and so on
so when I look at my performance metrics
I always want to see like okay if
there's a performance hotspot showing up
or some slowness showing up it had
better be in a routine that I know is
purposely some n cubed thing that I know
I can just replace or something if it's
showing up diffusely throughout the
program in general that's a big no for
me and I would fix it so I do have some
objective things however I don't know
that there's objective ways of measuring
really things like readability right
it's very hard to measure those things I
mean you can measure that with
experiments as this yes but they're hard
to conduct routinely okay and then a
question related to what you're saying
before is like a friend of mine a few
days ago it was actually mentioning
about this interview and we were
chatting about potential questions and
he said after all these years I think in
terms of sending messages to delegates I
can open the box and build functions but
my brain thinks methods so this to me
seems to be that is about familiarity
somehow the way we are used to do stuff
so what do you think about the link
between the perception we have about
good code and our familiarity with
specific Technologies is there a link in
your view there well I mean I think
there has to be I mean I think it's
undeniable that there is some link there
and the reason that I say that is just
to again to go back to the language
analogy
I mean there's just no question that I'm
never going to speak another language as
well as I speak English it's just not
it's just not right it's too late at
this point now if when I had been raised
I was taught Italian and English at the
same time or something then maybe I can
have an honest opinion about those two
that has nothing to do with my
familiarity of it or something like that
right but in general the languages that
I know or the the paradigms that I know
the idioms that I know I'm obviously
going to be more effective in than the
ones that I don't know
I have a lot of experience with object
oriented programming one of the reasons
I feel very comfortable critiquing is
because I've written large I shipped the
first version of a character animation
system was object oriented programming
one of the big reasons that I don't like
it is because when I actually went
through and analyzed all the problems
they all basically had to do with that
and when we removed it for the second
version it was a massively more
successful product with much higher
performance that was trivial to maintain
whereas before it was the all those
things were the opposite right and so it
comes from my experience with these
things and being fairly confident that
just there are much better ways to do it
inside of these particular paradigms but
I think once you step outside of those
paradigms we just don't know like I have
no ability to comment on on functional
programming right I just don't because I
don't have enough experience with it to
say that this or that would be the right
way to do it okay
okay now let's move on and talk a bit
more about performance itself yeah
so I guess I suspect I know the answer
to the first question maybe mine but
I'll ask it anyway if you I think you
touch upon these before
because sometimes and I see this very
often many say computers are quite
powerful nowadays so why should we be
worrying about performances you know if
our code is readable we use these
techniques that makes this much more
readable you know we use lots of
inheritance just to and for us this
makes our code better in our particular
context and the result is acceptable to
end users
why should we care about performances if
if all these things are verified so um
true meaning that the result is fine for
the end users then you actually don't
have a problem and I and I certainly
don't have a problem with it however
it's never the case so in that video the
performance excuse is debunked that is
one of the ones I tackle and I literally
show that Google Microsoft Facebook they
have
presented consistently they are like we
have research showing that no matter how
fast our software gets if we make it
faster users are more engaged with our
products they do more operations et
cetera et cetera right that's fine so
when I say acceptable it's kind of the
users are willing to live with that you
know it's kind of okay it's fine for us
then you're missing a huge business
opportunity is what I would say because
the research is 100 conclusive on this
that the more responsive your software
and the faster it performs the more
engaged users are the more likely they
are to spend more money using buying
more things for your software getting
more contracts adding more seats or in
the case of what is today's software
model there's oftentimes a lot of sort
of upsell to it right I mean if you look
at consumer facing software as opposed
to business software you are actually
trying to get users to look at ads or go
to a particular thing or buy a premium
version all of those things
no one as far as I know has suggested
that it is not true that higher
performance equals more money it's just
straight across the board even Adobe
says this right and they are shipping
basically Monopoly apps into a creative
space they're just like performance
equals money you want it so I would say
that the day has not yet arrived when
the performance is so blazingly fast no
matter what code you type in that we've
maxed out that that would be a great day
because then we can stop having podcasts
like this or be posting videos because
all software will be instant but we're
nowhere close right now we're nowhere
close to that now
this is more about Network I guess more
than IO because many modern Enterprise
systems let's call it I mean let's call
them like that you know with the big
companies offering Services maybe to
other companies or twend users
many of them nowadays are basically a
mesh of services talking via the network
with each other you're talking about
like microservices kind of sort of thing
microservice is kind of or distributed
monolith more frequently this kind of
stuff
have you got any suggestions on how to
approach designing for performance in
those situations
well the questions
essentially broad because performance
tends to be something that's somewhat
specific
so it really depends on which one of
those you're talking about so if it's a
actual microservices model
we already have examples of people
switching away from microservices to
monolith and getting faster the reason
for this is obvious is because hey the
network is slower than in memory so if
you combine things together they can
process more quickly this is not
surprising right
the way I like to say this is
microservices are not a software
engineering solution for the computer
they're a software engineering solution
for Conway's law they're something that
is there to solve a problem that a
business has of the form we have one
team that's going to do this micro
service and we have one team that's
going to do this microservice and having
a cut between them is our way of solving
an org chart problem which is Conway's
law
so microservices in my opinion never
were a thing you would do because you
wanted to write good software they're a
thing you do because your org chart it
makes that a more logical thing for you
to ship because it naturally breaks down
the program in the same way your org
chart is broken down again this is just
Conway's law I have a I have another
video on Conway's law in fact if you've
never heard of it if a listener's never
heard of it they can go watch that one
and I explain that one but it's it's one
of the most true laws in software
architecture so it's not surprising that
you can merge two Services together and
get optimization this is really just
another it's exactly like my clean code
horrible performance video when you
consider things as having to be
artificially separate it gets slower
almost always the only time it doesn't
get slower is if you know that the
amount of processing work that they will
share is never there's no overlap right
but if there was ever a Time when these
two things could be processed more
efficiently by considering together you
are strictly making the code slower by
separating them microservices are
literally that just in the network
structure as opposed to in your data
structure in a program you had it
separate one which was distributed
monolith well it's it's I'm saying that
it's the one that you find more often
yeah so many teams want to go through
microservices but they end up with
a match that where the service is
actually depend very
strongly from each other yeah to the
point so yeah I would say I don't know
that my I don't know that I have any
specific recommendation other than I
think it's not a great way to solve an
engineering problem but I understand why
it happens right it's Conway's law is
actually a real problem and I think the
way I put it in that the video that I
did on Conway's law was that
as long as we understand that what we're
doing is making the code worse but it's
the only way that our Aura can function
if you keep that mindset it's not
necessarily A Bad Thing meaning you can
make a decision to separate something
and know that the code is going to be
not as good as a result but that was the
only way you could figure out how to
structure your organization to get it
done then that may be true right we're
not miracle workers right we can't just
suddenly say that we're going to
engineer all this stuff perfectly
because that simply might be too
difficult and that's the original
Conway's law paper impact of the choice
of programming languages on on system
design and performance
do you think there are aspects due to
the languages themselves that you need
to to consider absolutely yes would you
suggest everybody to use only C plus
plus and avoid Java or okay what kind of
yeah what do you see as an impact I can
give you also some maybe an example I
can I can give a yeah I can give a sort
of broad answer to that sure
so I think this again is really just
comes down to what I hope people would
do more I guess is what I'd say
that they haven't been doing
it's not so much that I I don't want
everyone to start programming C plus in
fact I don't really like C plus plus
very much to be honest I program in a
very like light C plus it's more a c
like right because I'm just like I don't
know about this and there are new
languages now right like some people
really like rust for example there's new
languages coming out that you know
people can consider and whatever so I
don't want to suggest that c plus is
somehow a great language I really don't
think it is but either way
I would just like people to understand
that the performance implications of a
language Choice can be very large for
example if you were to program in Python
and run it uncompiled like you're
literally just running python as Python
and you don't go get mojo or something
or try to use cython or something like
this it's literally a hundred X slower
than the same code written in C not 2x
slower not 10x slower but like it's a
hundred times slower to go through an
interpreter for python because that's
just it doesn't jit right
and that doesn't mean you can't use
Python what it means is that if you're
going to actually use interpreted python
in a project you should know that fact
so what I object to is people saying
they don't have to know that or care
about that because they do if they know
that then they can make an informed
decision they can be like oh well
realistically how much code in this
project really is going to be written in
Python is it mostly going to always call
out to other libraries that are not
written in Python am I sure that there's
not going to be feature creep and we end
up with way more python than we think
we're going to have right can you make
these kinds of guarantees and maybe they
can and then no harm done they knew it
was 100 times slower they actually did
the work to verify that that was not
going to be a problem for this project
and then they made the project and it
was fine right
the thing I object to is the not knowing
and claiming that it will be fine it
won't be we have so many examples of
this like I said that performance
excuses debunked video I go through
example after example after example of
exactly that choice
PHP it'll be fine just use it no it
won't right and then you have to go
through all of these in fact I guess you
might say one of the things that is at
least a bright spot here is that people
are learning this they have now
optimized PHP a lot right python is now
getting things like Mojo and things like
cython to try and make it not as big a
deal right so we are learning but what I
would like people to do is to be aware
of these things before choosing a
language because you don't want to
choose a language and go in blind you
don't want to go I'm sure it will be
fine if you haven't actually had the
performance experience and knowledge to
know that it will be because you are
basically setting yourself up for one of
these big rewrites where someone has to
come in and rewrite all the PHP code or
like Facebook had to do make a special
compiler
just for them to speed up their PHP code
because it was too slow right those are
huge engineering undertakings that
you're basically foisting on someone
else by making that bad decision up
front Okay and I guess a similar
considerations may may be made about
other technology choices and like
Frameworks libraries the kind of
hardware
anything like that I think I guess we
can make the same kind of consideration
so the programming language is one
aspect but then if you're some
particular libraries you are saying
python if you use the libraries that are
actually C native libraries we may be
fine depending on what we need to do
depending what you need to do if you use
well even pure python ones we may be
fine but in some occasions they may be a
bit too slow because it's like 100 times
lower is quite a bit depending on what
you need to achieve exactly it's really
just about this is literally why I made
the course
I feel like the thing that's missing
these days is not actually optimization
work because that's a separate thing
what it is is just awareness it's
awareness of how much it costs to do
these different things because if you
know how much these things cost and can
actually account for them
then you may make a decision that is
quote unquote bad for performance
meaning it will yield worse performance
yes but if you know the bounds of that
you can really decide to do it because
you are actually making a real trade-off
what you cannot do is not know and claim
you're making a trade-off if you don't
know how bad the performance will be
from your decisions you aren't making a
trade-off what you're doing is just
ignoring a problem right so when people
say like oh I'm going to use this
particular coding practice and I'm not
going to worry about the performance of
it because it's a trade-off well if the
person really knows exactly how much
performance they're giving up there then
yes that was a trade-off and it may very
well be a valid one but on the other
hand if they don't actually know and
they don't measure these things and and
aren't familiar with how much
performance they're giving up that
wasn't a trade-off that was just a
random choice right yeah okay now that
you mention trade-offs we actually have
questions about trade-offs as you you
introduced the subject perfect segment
happy to help so and actually we're just
mentioning techniques and things so they
were just now when you say people are
not really knowing the trade-off so so
what are the common misconceptions that
or pitfalls related to good code that
developers should be aware of
specifically regarding performance I can
give you the number one there is a
glaring one which I would like to make a
video of and I just haven't quite gotten
around to it yet but it is it is
literally there is literally one which
is the biggest most damaging one ever
so at one point
Donald knuth the professor of Stanford
University of course famously wrote the
basically reference group I see in your
bookshelf it's right behind you yes yeah
yeah yeah you've got the fool she at one
point was quoting sir Tony when he
said premature optimization is the root
of all evil
right
this is a very common phrase I'm
assuming you've heard it well actually I
can tell you that Donald wrote that in a
in a paper in 1974 yes and it was a
quote it was he was calling somebody
else programming with go-to statements I
can give you the entire quote because I
had a question about that quote so you
can you are preempting me so off you go
continuous I apologize I didn't mean to
steal your thumb you don't have to
apologize it's fine
so if you read the context
of that quote
and what they were actually talking
about both of them
it's very clear what they meant and by
the way I happen to agree with it it
would be kind of foolish not to agree
with with them they are two of the best
most famous programmers who ever lived
what they meant was that when you write
code
there are optimizations you can make
that are like Assembly Language level
optimizations that will make the code
quite brittle and also quite difficult
to read and I've had to write code like
this in the past once or twice when you
have like some routine that is
absolutely critical to the performance
and you know you can squeeze an extra 20
30 out of it or something if you go in
and hand optimize this thing really
carefully or whatever right but it's
going to be a mess after that because
you've done all this you had to maybe
reorganize some data you're using all
kinds of stuff nowadays you're using
simdi and you've got all these kind of
things going on in there that make it
very hard for anyone to read and you
have to comment it so you remember what
the heck was going on in there right
and what they were talking about in that
quote was that they were basically
saying like look
don't do that to code
before you know that that code actually
runs often and actually accounts for
performance that matters to you right
don't just do that because you know what
I mean that's what they meant they I
mean I'm paraphrasing a bit but that's
the context that they were talking about
it in yeah I can tell you that in the
full quote from not basically he said
that we should forget about small
efficiency say about 97 percent of the
time
and says premature optimization is the
root of all evil yet we should not pass
up our opportunities in that critical
three percent yes and I think this is
literally what he was talking right he
was like in some small percentage of the
code
hand optimizing it is gonna matter and
you should do it but don't just hand
optimize some routine because now you're
into hand optimization because you're
making life worse for everybody else
because now they have to deal with this
really intricate code you've written
that is harder to maintain harder to
read all the things that clean code
people claim about the code they're
replacing is actually true about that
kind of code it's very hard to work with
and I say that as someone who has had to
write it I I really do think that you
don't want to have to do that to code
unless you know that you need to right
yeah however the way this quote is now
applied is that you don't need to think
about optimization until the end of your
program basically what people think they
meant by that is that you don't need to
think about performance when you write
your code you just write whatever you
want and then at some point in the
process when you then go measure there
will be a few hot spots and you do some
optimization on that or someone else
does the optimization on that and you're
done they did not mean that right that
is totally not what they meant and in
fact Rico Mariani I believe posted a
thing where he actually talked to Tony
horror about this and he was very upset
that people were taking it that way
because I mean
Donald news has all of his stuff as an
assembly in his books do you really
think this person is someone who would
say don't think about optimization or
performance when you're designing your
program it's like of course not they
would be horrified I think to know that
people were interpreting that quote to
mean that you don't have to think about
performance when you architect your
program I think I mean I would love to
hear from them directly I mean they
don't really speak in public much
anymore but
I'm pretty sure they would say no of
course when you architect your program
you should be thinking about performance
if you don't think about performance
when your architecture program you're
going to get into a situation where no
amount of hotspot optimization will ever
improve its performance and so to me
that is like the number one worst Folly
that we have nowadays is people thinking
that they don't have to architect for
performance up front you absolutely do
what you don't have to do is hand
optimize the code that is something that
you only need to do in those very
specific Hot Spot cases but architecting
for performance needs to be done from
day one so let's see if I understand
what you mean here so architecting of
performance as I see this from day one
is basically using the appropriate data
structures for the problem you're
solving for example so I've come across
called in the past where people should
have used sites instead of use vectors
in C plus plus causing a horrible
slowdown of the system and things like
this so I think here is if I understand
you correctly the architecting for
performance is is not thinking that I
should remove DC from here and
absolutely because blah blah blah is
more kind of let's do the right thing
the kind of obvious readable writing and
then if we need to do something specific
that requires some hand tuning and
possibly introducing some unreadable
code there has to be a very strong
reason for that this is the way I'm
interpreting it yeah I would say yes but
I would also add something to that which
is that you want your architecture to
naturally Force things into segments
that you know will need to be optimized
meaning when you are architecting a
program it's critical for you to have an
awareness of all of the different things
that probably will cause you performance
problems so you need to kind of be aware
like where am I processing large numbers
of things where am I doing things that
could have serial dependency chains like
I do one thing and wait for the result
kind of stuff those are almost the more
important things because if someone used
Vector instead of set for example I
agree that's bad bad because now I have
to go through and change all of these
places that used it and it's a pain you
don't really want to have to do that so
I agree it would be great if we didn't
have that problem but to me that's
almost not as bad of a problem as we
designed this whole thing to basically
be like oh I don't know I have this
object that I just like make a function
call on and it gives me back this thing
and unbeknownst to me that does a
network request every time or something
right because now all of my code is
using these objects and it's all written
serially and now someone comes and they
have to optimize it but the only way to
optimize it is to aggregate those
requests that's basically a complete
rewrite because the code is serially
waiting on them so there's no way for
that object to even batch them up
because they need the result right away
and you don't know how to break that
right the problem is that most people
seem to ignore these aspects so it seem
to think that all these things come for
free you do that there is no price to
pay and this is the biggest problem I
think you seem to be heavy with the
approach I mean correct it's like the
only problem I'm having with the
approach because in general like I said
I don't think we have objective measures
of code quality Beyond performance we
can measure the performance directly
obviously otherwise it's very hard to
objectively measure the performance so
if someone says that this is a more
readable style or that they can write
more quickly in this style they may well
be right I'm not in a position to tell
them that they're wrong about that even
if they are wrong about that I can't
prove it so really what I'm talking
about is just the fact that there are
objective things we can measure which
are runtime costs for these things and
cost to the structure of the program in
terms of performance we can measure
those so you need to know those and if
you do know those and still think that
it's a good choice to use whatever it is
that this other structure that you're
going to use that has a negative in that
objective metric if you are aware of
that and make that choice with full
knowledge then that is truly a trade-off
and you can call it a trade-off and
that's valid if you don't know those
things then really what you're doing is
making an excuse you're you're not
making a trade-off because you don't
know what you've traded you're just
making excuse to not know this other
thing and that's very bad and can have
very bad results okay and so here's
another question to us but I think I
probably know the answer but this was
about more the trade-offs with
developers time Computing course and
this kind of things so nowadays most of
the time developers time is actually
much more expensive than Computing costs
so I guess that following practices that
help cognition seem to be often a good
trade-off for many companies I guess I
would disagree there's two ways I would
disagree with that though one is that I
actually don't find that I have one meta
disagreement and one practical
disagreement The Meta disagreement is
that a lot of people say that they're
doing things that improve cognition but
I have not seen the evidence that it
improves cognition so that's just so I
might dispute the premise of many
people's claims that that is what
they're doing because yeah I was basing
this all on them you know the research I
mentioned before that since that at
least many clinical practices actually
help cognition in some ways so I was
supposed to wonder though right that's
the other problem compared to what right
well compared to not using them do
something else I would imagine so people
but there was a something else right in
other words that something else may not
have been the best example of what you
can do with code that is more performant
right that that is a fair that is a fair
injection yeah but anyway we can put
that aside let's assume that it actually
is helping developer cognition yeah the
problem that I have with that is that it
doesn't actually work in the real world
so this is what I tried to show in that
performance excuses debunked video
people claim that they're saving
development time but then you look at
their history and they've had to throw
out their entire system not once not
twice but oftentimes three or four times
in the space of 10 years for performance
so they claim that they were saving
develop first time but they're spending
years rewriting entire systems so I
dispute any claim that says that we are
saving developers time because the only
way you're saving developers time is if
you then don't have to do these huge
performance rewrites but you are so I
don't think the actual facts on the
ground support a claim of saving time
because maybe you saved some time the
first time you wrote it but then you
wrote it three more times
so I don't know man like I don't think
that was a savings if it had taken us
twice as long to write it the first time
but we actually didn't have to rewrite
it several times after that that would
have been a net savings now what I will
say is that let's say that being sloppy
gets you to Market fast your first time
right this is the thing that might
happen we need to get to Market quickly
we gotta ship this thing in six months
we're just not that good at architecting
for performance maybe we don't even have
anyone who knows how to do performance
architecture in the first place that's a
real scenario that can happen my hope is
that like I said one of the reasons I
made a course is I would like to educate
people about this stuff so that that's
not a situation people find themselves
in so that they can just kind of
naturally make systems that are better
for performance and they don't have to
make that choice but let's say you do
have to make that choice that's valid if
you just have to do something to get to
market now and you kind of know it's but
it's like we just have to do it that is
a valid position and it is borne out by
the facts on the ground there are plenty
of companies that had to do that and
then pretty much what you'll see is two
or three years after that they announced
they had to rewrite everything for
performance but that could be a strategy
right that could be a valid strategy
because when we look at the history of
successful software companies we see
this pattern a lot above having to
rewrite what I would say to that is to
me though that's still an opportunity it
says to me that we could improve
software engineering by figuring out how
to make the default way that people
program more perform it by education by
making languages more efficient by
default you're not giving people a
really slow PHP at the outset making it
so that we make the decision so that PHP
when it's released is faster because in
general we have a more of a cultural
performance so they're not going to ever
have languages sitting in front of them
that are slow by Design or something
like that so to me even though I do
think it's valid to take an approach of
slow poorly performing version one try
to follow it up with a version two
that's fast that happens a lot in
practice I still think of that now
though that's an opportunity an
opportunity for us to fix something
about the way we're developing software
because I don't think it has to be that
way I just think that our current
programming practices and tools
encourage that and we can shift that we
can make it better than that okay and
now we've got actually the last question
that is really related to this is what
is a good approach in your view to
include performance considerations when
designing a system so a team is starting
with a Greenfield system what should
they do so they don't forget about
performances it's pretty tough if I had
a one sentence answered that I wouldn't
have made the course I think that the
only real answer to that is you have to
educate yourself about how Modern
Performance actually works you need to
know something about how CPUs work and
what they can and can't do quickly you
need to know something about how
compilers work and what they can and
can't transform into efficient code and
you need to know something about those
serial dependency chains so that you
know that you can't just hide Network
requests and wait for return values
because it simply won't ever be fast no
matter what someone then tries to do to
it you have to do these things in
parallel and so understanding this what
I would say is the I'm pretty sure the
only answer to this is not here's an
approach it's rather programmers have to
include performance education as a core
thing that they do like when we consider
someone qualified to do computer science
they come out of a degree program or
they whatever or they're working in a
company it should just be considered a
thing that they need to know is how to
Think Through the performance issues
that they might face
and it's not that hard it's not compared
to learning all of some modern language
like C plus with its thousands of
features and stuff it's not that hard to
think because CPUs actually have to be
kind of simple like they're way more
complicated than they were but they're
nowhere near as complicated as a modern
language right so it's not that hard to
kind of learn like okay here's how these
i o subsystems work here's how the CPU
Works here's how the compiler works I
basically get it and now I can just when
I program I can kind of keep in the back
of my head
a vague understanding of what's going to
have to happen as a result of my
decisions and then I think people just
kind of naturally would move away from
big serial dependency chains on iO and
lots and lots of waste like you know big
interpreters in the way or language
features that can't be optimized as an
industry we'd start to move away from
that and then it would get a lot easier
for everybody because if we're all
operating with that knowledge you're not
going to get slow Frameworks anymore
right the Frameworks are going to be
fast because the people who made them
were thinking it through so I think we
just kind of need a cultural shift I
don't think there's this like here's an
approach it's like no you kind of have
to learn it and once you learn it the
approach kind of becomes self-evident
because you just kind of know like oh
all right if I do this I'm obviously
creating a huge problem for my CPU so
I'm not going to do that right and I
don't know that there's another way
around it because it's easy to take any
piece of code and make it very slow just
by making a few bad decisions and
without understanding why those things
are happening at the CPU level it's
pretty hard for you to guess what
they'll be but once you know what the
CPU has to do it's actually quite easy
okay thank you
thank you so well I think we've been a
hard listeners quite a bit of food for
thought okay it's been quite an
interesting conversation for me but I've
I've a very
quick question the last one very short
answer on this one if there was one
thing you'd like a software engineer
that was listening to to this podcast to
remember from this show yeah what would
that be I think it would be that
performance really matters in practice
and we have copious data that says that
that's true so I would encourage
everyone to actually learn about
performance because
the idea that you can ignore it which is
kind of very culturally common nowadays
is simply not borne out by what we
actually see happening in business I
mean so that's what I would say please
look at the actual evidence and see how
much performance really matters to lots
of companies because it does matter and
I think that it would be better if
engineers in general took the time to
really understand it okay thanks cousin
so where can people find out more so I
think they can follow you on Twitter
you've got a Twitter handle and but then
also is there any other
way to get in touch with you the course
and stuff that I mentioned and just my
public posts are on computer
enhanced.com you can just type in
computer enhanced.com and it goes there
and that's where I post anything that's
of any value is what I post there I will
put everything on the link section of
the podcast and that's it that's
everything okay thanks a lot kezi for
coming to the show it's been quite a
real pleasure that's been it's been my
pleasure thank you for having me thank
you very much and this is Johannes Bruni
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening